Guide to the New York Revolutionary Groups collection, 1966-1971.
New York Revolutionary Groups collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
New York Revolutionary Groups collection, 1966-1971.
8118
Kugelberg, Johan,
1.9
Printed material, publications, photocopies, newspapers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Materials documenting influential radical groups of the 1960s. The collection includes a complete run of Black Mask and 61 issues of Rat Subterranean News, 90 flyers and handbills relating to the New York anarchist groups Black Mask and Up Against the Wall Motherfuckers, as well as related affinity groups and others such as the Yippies, ESSO (The East Side Service Organization, or the East Side Survival Organization), and New York Provo.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Black Mask was a radical group and newspaper created in 1966 by abstract painter Ben Morea, poet Dan Georgakas, and Ron Hahne. Inspired by the actions of the French Situationists and Dutch Provos among others, Black Mask produced a ten issue run newspaper and some broadsheets before going underground. Morea, along with some others involved with Black Mask emerged as the Up Against The Wall Motherfuckers, a name taken from the poem "Black People!" by Amiri Baraka (then still known as LeRoi Jones). In the late 1960s these groups became infamous for actions such as dumping uncollected trash from the Lower East Side in the fountain at Lincoln Center and organizing a protest of The Filmore East through a series of free concerts offered to promote community use of the venue.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Materials documenting influential radical groups of the 1960s. The collection includes a complete run of Black Mask and 61 issues of Rat Subterranean News, 90 flyers and handbills relating to the New York anarchist groups Black Mask and Up Against the Wall Motherfuckers, as well as related affinity groups and others such as the Yippies, ESSO (The East Side Service Organization, or the East Side Survival Organization), and New York Provo.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Kugelberg, Johan,; Morea, Ben.; Black Mask (Group of artists).; Up Against the Wall Motherfuckers (Gang).; Youth International Party.
Subjects:
Anarchists.; Anarchism.; Anarchism -- New York (State) -- New York.; Anarchism -- United States.; Internationale situationniste.; Protest movements.; Social movements.; Radicalism.; Radicalism -- New York (State) -- New York.; Radicalism -- United States.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Related collections: #8111, Situationist Collection and #8060, Johan Kugelberg punk collection.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I: Fliers, 1968, Undated
  - Fliers by Up Against the Wall, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Western Union telegram with a message to Mayor Richard J. Daley, 1968-08-30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Yippie fliers, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Fliers, handbills, and press releases printed by The Open Press relating to New York Provo", Undated; Open Press (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Additional fliers, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Oversized fliers, 1968, Undated
    - Fliers by Up Against the Wall, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Additional Yippie fliers, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - The Open Press, New York Provo, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Handbills issued under Newspaper of The Streets, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Black Mask posters/fliers, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - King Mob Echo #1, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - King Mob #3, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Special issue on Black Mask and UAWMF
    - King Mob #6, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Two letters on Student Power, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Supplement to November 1968 issue of King Mob Echo #1
    - King Mob / The Black Hand Gang, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Zine of radical political cartoons
    - Additional fliers, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series II: Publications, 1966-1968, Undated
  - Nouvelles, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    A French student publication with coverage of Black Masks's MoMa action
  - Thutch 666, Undated; Leake, Jonathan; Black Flag Press (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The only issue of Up Against The Wall Motherfucker, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Life Chants And Songs of The Revolution, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Mimeograph booklet with contributions by Black Mask, Julian Beck, Paul Prensky, and others
  - Black Mask issues 1-10, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - It Was Meant To Be Great But It's Horrible, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    "Flier related to King Mob's Selfridge's action, similar event put on by the Yippies and Black Mask"
  - 2 Yippie articles from The Guardian, 1968-03-30 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 2 NY Times articles concerned with the political activism of Hippies, 1968-03-24-1968-03-26 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper clipping featuring a photograph of Abbie Hoffman, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Hoffman, Abbie
  - Goodbye To All That, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Pamphlet reprinting material from the Rat regarding its takeover by an allwomen’s collective in January 1970
  - East Village Other, vol. 4, no. 46, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - East Village Other, vol. 4, no. 51, 1969-11-19 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Cover story on the Rat
  - Finger, vol. 2, no. 5, 1970-01 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    "An independent Alternative High School paper"
  - Intercourse, no. 4, Spring 1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Contains a Provo article
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, no. 1, 1968-03-04 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, no. 2, 1968-03-18 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, no. 2 i.e. 3, 1968-03-22-1968-04-04 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 4, 1968-04-5-1968-04-18 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 5, 1968-04-19-1968-04-30 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 6, 1968-05-03-1968-05-16 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 7, 1968-05-17-1968-05-30 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 8, 1968-06-01-1968-06-14 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 9, 1968-06-15-1968-06-28 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 10, 1968-07-01-1968-07-15 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 12, 1968-07-26-1968-08-08 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 14, 1968-08 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 16, 1968-09-06-1968-09-19 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 17, 1968-09-20-1968-10-03 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 18, 1968-10-04-1968-10-17 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 19, 1968-10-18-1968-10-31 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 20, 1968-11-01-1968-11-14 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 21, 1968-11-15-1968-11-28 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, 23, 1968-12-13-1969-01-02 (Box 3)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, no. 26, 1969-01-24-1969-01-30 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, no. 27, 1969-01-31-1969-02-06 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 1, no. 29, 1969-02-14-1969-02-20 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 2, no. 2, 1969-03-14-1969-03-21 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 2, no. 3, 1969-03-28-1969-04-03 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 2, no. ?, 1969-04-17 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 2, no. 7, 1969-05-02-1969-05-08 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 2, no. 8, 1969-05-09-1969-05-15 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 2, no. 9, 1969-05-16-1969-05-22 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 2, no. 10, 1969-05-23-1969-05-29 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 2, no. 12, 1969-06-12-1969-06-18 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 2, no. 13, 1969-06-19-1969-07-03 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 2, no. 14, 1969-07-09-1969-07-23 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, 1969-08-12-1969-08-26 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, 1969-08-27-1969-09-09 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, 1969-09-10-1969-09-23 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 2, no. 19, 1969-10-08-1969-10-21 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 2, no. 21, 1969-10-29-1969-11-12 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 2, no. 22, 1969-11-12-1969-11-25 (Box 4)
  - Rat Subterranean News, 1970-01-07-1970-01-20 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 2, no 27, 1970-02-06-1970-02-23 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 2, no 28, 1970-02-24-1970-03-09 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, 1970-03-07-1970-03-21 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, 1970-03-20-1970-04-04 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, 1970-04-04-1970-04-18 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, 1970-05-08-1970-05-21 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, 1970-05-22-1970-06-04 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, 1970-06-05-1970-06-19 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, 1970-06-26-1970-07-10 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, 1970-08-09-1970-08-23 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, 1970-09-11-1970-09-25 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, 1970-10-06-1970-10-27 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 3, no. 15, 1970-10-29-1970-11-18 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 3, no. 16, 1970-11-17-1970-12-06 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 3, no. 17, 1970-12-17-1971-01-06 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 3, no. 18, 1971-01-12-1971-01-29 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 3, no. 19, 1971-02-03-1971-02-20 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 3, no. 20, 1971-03-02-1971-03-23 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 3, no. 21, 1971-03-30-1971-04-21 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 3, no. 22, 1971-05-03-1971-06-01 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 3, no. 23, 1971-06-14-1971-07-10 (Box 5)
  - Rat Subterranean News, vol. 3, no. 24, 1971-08 (Box 5)
- Series III: Exhibit material, 2012-2013
  - Exhibit labels and related material, 2013-2013 (Box 6)
    Boo-Hooray’s 2012/2013 exhibition "Opposition: Black Mask, Ben Morea, and U.A.W.M.F."